[Music]
hello and welcome everyone
this is actinflab livestream number 36.2
it's january 26 2022.
welcome to active inference lab
we are a participatory online lab that
is communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference you can find us
at the links here on this page
this is a recorded and an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome
and we'll be following good video
etiquette for live streams
check out activeinference.org if you
want to learn more about what active lab
is up to or if you want to participate
in any of the activities which include
live streams in the communications
organizational unit but a ton of other
stuff is happening
today in 36.2 our third discussion on 36
we're going to continue to
learn and discuss this paper by sims and
pizzulo 2021
modeling ourselves
what the free energy principle reveals
about our implicit notions of
representation and
we're gonna have a
nice jumping off dot two as we do
and have some questions written down and
prepared
other things will spontaneously arise
and if anyone watching live wants to
just write a question in a live chat we
can also address that
we'll start with an introduction so
we'll go around and introduce ourselves
people can say anything they want and
they can also add just what got them
excited about the paper in general or
for this dot to discussion specifically
so
i'm daniel i'm a researcher in
california
and
just excited to see
how this representation
discussion influences our
own self
representation and
that at the individual and the lab scale
moving forward i'll pass it to blue
hi i'm blue i'm a independent research
consultant in new mexico and i am
excited by this paper because in our
previous discussions we're as usual left
with more questions than answers and
also i kind of um
i'm finding myself like swayed by the
different like representational
structural content driven
non-representational like these
different arguments and i just find them
very interesting and i just want to know
if at the end of this if i'll be swayed
more or less in certain directions or
maybe just be more open to
other interpretations of fep
and i will pass it to danielle
hello i'm danielle i'm a cognitive
scientist at google with a background in
language evolution language development
i'm really interested in
thinking about how humans evolve the
ability to model other minds so
interested in how this this discussion
can contribute to that and generally
interested in how
really good frameworks like the fep can
help um kind of encompass other
frameworks and and revise them
awesome dean
hi i'm dean i'm up here in calgary
in canada and
uh
a little bit of recency effect i started
watching ozark the
last season and so i i'm trying to plug
this paper in through what would marty
bird do
so that's kind of my little twist on
modeling so
back to you daniel
who is marty bird and what would he do
right
exactly
great question well that's all we
prepared for today so
we'll go into the discussion
but
we have some things written down is
there anything just off the bat
that anybody wants to just ask or jump
into or like a figure or a quotation to
begin with or we can
look at some of the things that we had
written down
okay let's just start with
what we've written down and then of
course at any point we can branch off
okay
i think a big
theme that we'll probably return to
again and again is this idea of
moving back and forth
from
non-representational forms to
representational forms
in the paper they introduce
four different facets of representation
and then
how each of those facets can be
approached in a representational or
non-representational way and although
the image here shows some solid black
lines
that was kind of the discussion was is
there movement across these areas or
blurriness so maybe
dean
what
is there to say or start to explore
with representations
emerging like almost precipitating or
crystallizing out of something
non-representational and then the
reverse process of something that is
more representational
submerging back into something that's
less
well one of the things the authors did
talk quite a bit about in terms of the
the functional aspect of this was the
vicarious nature and then they also
talked quite a bit about
whether or not somebody who's sort of
moving in that
radical and activism
space um still has to be able to
differentiate and get some some include
some of the
temporal aspects of what might pop up
and
become something that we can stabilize
and in
model representation form
but then it has to also be able to
disappear right it also has to not
necessarily consume everything in terms
of our our attentional fields so
i'm not really sure exactly
how that
works itself through
[Music]
but i would think that it's difficult to
say that
even if we're in a flow state
that there isn't some
moment when we
do reflect in that mirror so
that's kind of where i'm at i i don't
have any answers per se but i
don't want to get stuck in the idea that
it's just a
on off switch i think that there's a bit
of a
a moment of dimming and then
re-re-lighting
so
that makes me think about certain
paths that our thought takes
over these eight cells
like when we're in the representational
side when we're dealing with a
representation how do we take that
tetrahedra and look at the four
different sides
and then how do we stay within a column
looking at just the organizational
aspects of a system and then move
north and south
on that
um
do these kinds of knowledge
or cognitive transitions
happen
all the time
do they have other
names that might be more familiar than
using some of this
philosophical language
like what is it are there any times in
our days
where we're dealing with something
representationally and we shift
to a non-representational
version
within one of these categories or across
categories
so i was just thinking of that actually
like um
what
does like organism organizational
an organizational representation look
like like that is like
a map like a structural organ
representation a content related
representation and a functional
representation and and
like what what do these representations
look like like
and how are they different
i was thinking about that
let's go to the definition of the
organizational representation just to
kind of
remember
the fact that fep requires internal
states
states that encode the recognition model
that are statistically separated from
the external reality
so the organizational
area
is about
how variables inside of systems are
separated from variables
outside of the system
the
pro representation take
is
there's an evidentiary boundary
the markov blanket
and there's something on the inside
that is doing something like a
representation on what's outside
so that's the pro representational take
then the
non-representational take is where we
get into the ecological and the
inactivist persuasion
and that's where the authors say that
some have approached this markov blanket
structural
formalism
even though we're talking about it in
the organizational not the structural
facet
in a manner that suggests a
non-representational view
and they argue that just partitioning
two coupled systems like agent and
environment
with a mark out blanket
doesn't imply
that the behavior of the agent
is explained by
anything related to an internal model
that's doing anything like capturing the
structure of
the outside world
so you just use like organizational and
structural like in this like big hobnob
but so my question was really
what does an organizational
representation look like and so
i'm hearing that you answered that there
are clearly defined boundaries in
organizational representation
or partitions between internal and
external studies so like i have a
clearly when i have a representation in
my mind that's organizational
it is
like your boundary is different from
like is it
only your own boundary or is it like the
boundaries of each individual agent are
organizationally represented in your
mind or is it just the boundary between
you and the outside world
and how might that differ from
structural and content related like what
do these different representations look
like that's what i'm trying to see like
would they be maps and how would the
maps be different
the structural which does come up
several times in
the organizational definition
so we see structure coming up the
structure of the system in how it's
organized but what is the structural
specifically okay
having representational vehicles that
are structurally similar to the state of
affairs in the world that they stand for
the pro-representational
structural side
is kind of like the good regulator
theorem of cybernetics
so the organizational side is
highlighting that there is some sort of
informational encapsulation we might
even say like our previous discussions
but some sort of
organization of variables such that
there's an inside and outside that are
separated
and
the structural side is saying that
um it's like if there's
three things that are connected in the
outside world
then the not just that there are
variables that are organizationally
separated in the internal states but
that the structure of those
isolated variables
is going to do something like
recapitulate or have a structural
resemblance
to the generative process
generative process that's like the niche
that's what's outside generative model
that's what the agent has on board
and so if it's to be useful for control
purposes then
it may have to have some sort of
structural resemblance to the actual
connectivity
of the generative process so
generative model and generative process
being separated is what's captured in
the organizational side
them having similar
resemblances or similar structures is
what the structural side is
the structural non-representationalists
are suggesting
this is i think tale of two densities
with ramstead at all or modeling
ourself author suggests that generative
models do not meet the requirements of
structural representations
because the process of exploitable
structural representations so posterior
beliefs in the
entity
is enacted
and so it doesn't necessarily have to
recapitulate the form of the generative
process so maybe one could
be skilled in the performance of driving
without having variables connected in
the way that a car
pieces are connected
it comes back to a theme that
active presents to us
perhaps more as a question than an
answer which is how much do we have to
know in order to act
do we have to have
an internal
model that is very similar to the
process
uncorrelated and how similar it is
anti-correlated in how similar it is
and can we have a framework as
researchers that helps us compare the
structure and organization of generative
processes and generative models of those
processes
yes um kill 14.
so i'll put this out there and then
people push back or say it doesn't make
any sense
from what i read in the paper now
because i had to go back over and look
at it again
if i were to try to draw a simple
comparison between organization and
structure
organization would you could see it as
being something as being either in or
out
so you could be inside
you could be inside a cell or outside of
a cell then in our minds we can tell
we will draw those partitions and then
we'll decide what's in or out
structural i think takes on more of the
entailing question something that serve
all brought up in the
chat which is
so once you've decided whether
something's in or not is there something
else that now can be seen as being super
ordinate to that
from us from
from the perspective of sort of what's
wrapped around
now the thing that's in or what can sit
upon
theoretically the thing that you've now
decided is is
foundational to whatever it is you're
looking at and what can be set aside as
not being important to what you're
looking at so again
pull that apart and say that that's
wrong but that's kind of what i try to
read into what the readers or what the
writers were saying so it's just my
interpretation
thanks blue
so i i just wonder in this
organizational representation is
do you draw a distinction between
i mean clearly there's one between like
what's internal and external to yourself
but are you also trying to like draw
distinctions between what's internal and
external to
your computer or your refrigerator or
your best friend or your child like are
you making a representation of
everything that's internal and external
to every other thing or is it only with
respect to your own
self versus environment
i would think it's it's when you do that
i don't know that it's
implied that you do it all the time
but if you choose to do that
i think that that's something that's
pretty easy to
tell the difference
around
so again i'm not sure that they were
saying that we do this we're do always
constantly doing this but i think
they're what they were trying to do is
show the difference between
knowing when something's in or out
versus knowing when something's first or
second
from a structural standpoint
again i don't want to put words in the
author's mouth
but i that's i did
i did hear that in the words that they
were doing to try to parse those two
things and give each each their due as
opposed to saying
they're just the same thing overlapping
let's try one
little thought loop
so let's start with
blue's question of what does an
organizational representation look like
so we'll start in that very top left
cell
and then
shift
the focus towards the structural
components
and then challenge the structural
representation
but stay within the structural domain
and then see if that can result to us
making it back to a non-representational
organizational uh framing
so what is a good organizational what's
something that is
classic vanilla organizational
representation
well
that's something that is well separated
in terms of variables inside and outside
the system so we're not worried about
the structure of the variables inside or
outside just that they are separated
so
computers seem like pretty clear cases
where within a program
you could have variables that by design
are
separated through like an intermediate
variable
or
computers and hardware
like two computer systems could be
totally separated except for an
interface like a usb port
or something but of course this paper
is about that strange loop
when
it's a cognizing agent
an adaptive active inference agent doing
that
representing not necessarily a
mere
active agent
but
should we
use a computational example or
some sort of um enocted human
example
but you got got a good example right
here on the page so how would we how
would we shift
across the y-axis between organizational
representational because i'm assuming
we're going clockwise from to
representational structural
that's not that's not a hard
example to to
make
yes um
yes so um in the
human
case this would be like um so two humans
in a conversation
they are in a conversation
yes
perfect outside of the conversation yes
two humans when two humans are in
conversation
right there is
separation
in terms of their sensory motor
systems
so
we have check the box for organizational
representational
starting in the top left cell
all right now the question would be
is there structural representation
so
that would be like maybe if one person
thought of a sentence and then said it
and then the other person
thought of that sentence too
would that qualify as a structural
representation because
there's a structural resemblance
in the model of the two
conversions
um yeah we could also find out if if
both of us were talking at the same time
and suddenly stopped turn taking that
the structure
of that
model would would now fundamentally
change it's still representational
and two people arguing over top of one
another
to the third party isn't necessarily
something comprehendable
never mind to the two people that are
inside the conversation right
blue
so
when i think about conversation
something comes to mind recently like
like really you need to have like the
order of the language specified like my
son is reading now and he's five um and
and you know he's taking the book like
pop on pop the dr seuss book and he'll
turn it upside down and he'll say dad no
dough and like we'll read it that way
and then he wants to read like every
sentence backwards like from the end to
the beginning which i'm like i don't
care as long as you're reading because
it gets them practicing reading but it's
it's completely
the context is completely um different
right when you're reading like each word
in the opposite order so like when
you're talking about a structural
representation of a conversation
i think that there needs to be like a
literal representation or at least like
a coarse grained representation of
in what order things are said in order
to glean some kind of meaning but then
are we bleeding into the content related
but like as we're you know that's why i
really feel like like what are these
different maps look like and trying to
maybe elucidate what the representations
are is valuable because i think when you
have organization okay inside outside
like this is this sentence or he said
this and she said that or or whatever
and then you try to put structure on it
like that gives it then content or
context that they can then you know and
so on and so forth
dean
no i i don't have much to add to that
other than i i just don't think that
that this loop that we've we've just
selected this we said there was going to
be certain amount of randomness in the
last live stream and we've chosen this
now let's walk let's walk through it
i don't see it being difficult
to to follow that path and find examples
so we have a super ordinate right now
structurally we want to carry out
this directionality from the
representational side of things to the
non-representational side and and blue
if you're if your kid wants to turn the
book upside down
that's that's actually a feature right
because they're not already stuck in
this
only one way of doing it things so
yeah
let's complete the red
loop
and then then the green of the orange
will come into play okay so we started
with two people in conversation that's
organizational separation of cognition
this brings us to
the structural facet which is
where there's a structural resemblance
in the representations of the
conversants
so they're
maybe
it is the case where they're both
thinking about a similar
topology of variables so there's some
structural representation
but now let's
stay within the structural column go
from b to c okay so the two people are
in a conversation it's kind of like a
dance
so what if those two people's
representation
is so different
that it's actually not structurally
resembling so maybe one person is um
the more experienced in the discipline
and the other is less experienced like
one person's super good at fixing motors
the other person is just has no idea
so
the representationalist take would be
like well they're both thinking about
the motor but then when we start to see
like
a cognitive asymmetry
all of a sudden
we fall out of structural
representationalist between these two
systems
because their cognitive models don't
necessarily have similar structure
yes danielle
oh wait unmute and then go for it
so um i might be missing something here
but i thought that we
can only start to talk about the
structural dimension here once
in this example the two people in the
conversation are representing the the
same thing and then the question is
how much information or how how does
each of their representations do each of
their representations have to look
similar to one another but like
part of it has to be that they are
representing the same thing is that
a sort of necessary component
if they're not representing the same
thing then we're having a different
conversation
well
that may come to the
functional
um
that might come to the content related
like the novice
and the expert
the representations are both about the
engine
but
they're so structurally different
in their representation of the engine so
that although the content in the
aboutness of the representation is
similar so still qualifying as a
representation
in that sense
there is a structural
non-resemblance such that by that
criteria in that situation we've fallen
out of the representational cell b
into
something non-representational
potentially blue what do you think
so i think like two people in a
conversation
can be trying to represent the same
thing like like yes they both need to be
trying to represent have the same
representation like they're trying to
converge on a conversation a meaningful
conversation presumably um but they
don't always converge and then that's
where you get like misunderstandings or
or like you know we both think that we
think the same
we both agree that we're thinking that
we have the same structural
representation but perhaps they're
different and then and then the
communication breaks down
okay
so the the um the structures are so
different
that we're
recognizing it as a continuum from total
overlap of structural resemblance to
total
um non-overlap but it would be important
to specify that null hypothesis
so we've kind of
scooted into c
how do we stay in that space of like the
novice and the expert who have different
cognitive representations and then use
that to challenge even
organizational
representationalism
blue then
oh dean first and then
go ahead
right i just thought i want to just go
back to the to danielle's point so if
we're if we're structuring a
conversation normally we turn take
but if we're playing in a band
we're all playing at once and then we
stop playing so i think we can start
with structure too it's just deciding
how we want to signal
right so i i don't think it i don't
think there's a necessarily an order
that we have to start with organization
first we can actually start with
structure first as well
yeah and i think a conversation is a
particularly challenging example because
we're representing two things but we're
representing what the other person is
trying to say and then presumably what
the conversation is about is something
else in the world that we could be
representing exactly yeah
blue
so i think we're representing um a
degree of of information sharing and i
think that this is going to like lump
into autopilesis which i i've been
really wanting to to kind of
get into but but when we have um like
i'm my own person and i'm communicating
with danielle from you know 50 000 miles
away we both
feel like we're getting on the same page
when we actually like do get on the same
page like do we form some kind of like
separate cognitive unit like at what
degree of of model overlap is the degree
of information sharing so high that then
we
are
worthy of our own markov blanket like
we're sure that we understand that we
are the same unit
right and i think that this idea of
self-assembly and information sharing
and model overlap like i think that
there's
um
an important um path to traverse down
this way because if you don't have full
overlap of the model like you're
or or do you need full overlap to form a
self-assembling system to be you know to
form a higher level it's just an
interesting thought
that's kind of where the c to d
transition takes us
which would be like
so we have
um
the drummer is waiting for this and has
a model resembling this and then the
singer has a totally different structure
and then when we think about the whole
cognitive system it
it doesn't deny what we recognize in a
that there still is like the sensory
motor separation
but we've reached that point
by those
people
or roles being
part of a larger
non-separable extended cognitive system
so almost by recognizing the interaction
so here we focused on the separation
in a and that's what granted us the
representational um
cell but we've returned
to
seeing that
partial information encapsulation
within some type of broader structure
where none of the entities have like the
band level representation
so hopefully other people can think of
other like abcd examples
but
when we were at b
we kind of started branching off into
like
talking about the content
related things the aboutness
so here it's like there it two people do
have a structural
resemblance in their internal model
and it's about
the same thing but then what if one
person
sees the aboutness in such a different
way
that again we fall out of the
content-related
representation
and then how would we move from there
back to c
where all of a sudden the cognitive
models in a sense don't have structural
representations
uh resemblance
because
they're
about different things now
danielle
so would this be like in the case of
two two things that are so analogous
that they share a lot of structural
similarities and thinking of like
dendrite gentner's work that
um
you can actually draw lines between the
individual aspects of of the concepts
but they could be about totally
different things um but two people
talking about these things can can form
some sort of structural similarity in
their representations and it's just like
an entry point into being able to think
about all other things um but the
aboutness really has nothing to do with
it
um
dean then i might want to ask me on that
i don't know i don't know if this
answers that danielle but
from my
space i'm thinking
the difference between say a distracted
driver who's looking down at their phone
between the seats and somebody's got
that information and heads up display on
their windshield
right so so content twice but
structurally presented one as a one as a
distracted state and one as a contiguous
state
so i don't know if that answers your
point but i think
we could
we know the difference right
in terms of what where the where the
content is structured and how we're
trying to
contextualize
each each matter so
again staying at this sort of
educational
setting
what
is it important to see a transference
or a new emergence of
is it that the
structural model of the learner
is moving into more resemblance
with
the teacher
is it that the aboutness of the learner
is moving towards the same aboutness of
the teacher
um or let's just remind about what the
functional is
supporting vicarious use before or in
the absence of external events
so does
the teaching
[Music]
conversation
um will it be
a functional representation
when
vicariously without the teacher the
student can
carry out what the teacher could do
which might be
having aboutness or not
it might be
with a structural cognitive resemblance
or not
it might involve
total
informational isolation
putting us squarely in a or it might
involve some
type of
challenging of that
in d
the reason why there's not going to be i
think a precise answer because
as the paper
lays out
even for the same scenario people do
have different perspectives so it's not
like we're trying to take a scenario
then classify it into well that one's
like an a b e g
or an a c e h like
that
is probably not
what one of the outcomes could be
but these are all
perspectives that we could take on a
given
scenario um
and they do reveal interesting things
about
the systems of studies
anything else to add on this sort of
like looping around the cells or should
we
push on
push
okay blue what were you thinking here
i was just taking notes uh and so like
if
so maybe we should talk about content
related and
functional so i was just taking notes on
um
you know what these are organizational
like how are the representations
and i was trying to draw a picture so if
you i will draw my picture if um
if you will talk about maybe functional
representation like what does a
functional representation look like or
content related what is it what's inside
of those and then i will draw my picture
and then you can show it all right
sure so the content related
is
whether the generative models need to
explicitly model
the ways external states produce
sensations
environmental models or the ways actions
produce sensations
is it really important that internal
states resemble
external states or is it sufficient
that they afford
accurate action control
so
um
let's just say there's a spotlight
that's shining
photons onto the eye
the content of the cognitive
representation
[Music]
would put us more
um we'd be more in the representational
camp
if the cognitive model were truly
explicitly modeling
the ways in which
the photons hit
the retina
maybe
but this or is a bit challenging because
the ways actions produce sensations that
could be a model of like well if i blink
it becomes darker and when i open my
eyes it's lighter
but that's a totally disjoint question
from understanding how a spotlight works
but those two scenarios of the
spotlight's cognitive
explicit modeling the environmental
model
or
the sensory motor model of blinking and
it becoming darker those are both
content
related and
dean
well i don't know if this helps or not
but um
one of the things that i used to bring
up around this this idea
was the
was the the puzzle concept i.e
so you got a box and it says a thousand
piece puzzle
and
when you open up the box
uh is that representational or is it not
representational until you've figured
out whether all thousand pieces have now
been
duly assembled right
so from a from a content perspective do
you have
what you need
in order to be able to tell the
difference between something which is
representative and that which is not
so again i don't know if that's helpful
in terms of sort of trying to see a
difference between that say in structure
like where it's placed
relative to the context or not but that
was the way i tried to
surface it
one
evolution or
handshake
that hinges on that ore
of the environmental models and the
sensory motor models they do unpack a
little bit
so one approach consists in starting
from the sensory motor models
so that would be when i blink
it becomes darker when my eyes are open
it's lighter
but progressively extends them to
incorporate extra variables that
describe external causes of sensation
so um
like
if there's um
a light on one side but not on the other
side
then it can be the case that that
blinking is
true no matter how you're turned
but then that could be enriched or
augmented with a model of
parameters that describes external
causes of sensation like there's a light
over there
and not over there and so actually that
little loop that we just took
was
from the sensory motor b
the sensory motor model in b
moving to a representational model
of
uh the content like there's a light over
there
and then
does that well at least the that was the
bte
move
but then maybe that could do
something else so maybe blue will
clarify there but let's go back to just
review functional
like
what is the functional and
it's good to revisit these in the zero
one 2
3 4 5 because it's the contribution of
the paper
and maybe there are other
facets other columns to add and there's
just a lot of
complexity even as this is
so the functional one
is about supporting vicarious use before
or the in the absence of external events
so in that story with the lights and the
blinking
it only ha that model only has to be
instantiated
while the in that room with the photons
hitting the eye and the blinking
happening
however
we can imagine a situation
that's vicariously detached
or before that setting like what would
happen if there were a light over here
and a light over here and it was the
case that blinking made it darker
and this is where they trace back to
piaget
that representations should vicariously
stand for
something external in their absence and
afford vicarious operations
so there's a light over on the left side
you reach over and you unscrew it
what is in your hands
now that is
um
seeming to be in the functional
facet because we're talking about
the role the representation is playing
and the fact that it is standing for
something external in the absence
there's no physical light that we're
talking about it's not like we're
unscrewing it and then verifying that
it's in our hand
who's for and against
that
what functional roles do internal models
play during free energy minimization
and does minimization require the
internal manipulation of variables
in ways that resemble vicarious
operations in the classical piaget
account of representation
yes blue
so
this might be like i don't know maybe
it's the easiest and also like the
hardest to
get
a grip on
so i think about um
like do we so if we have a
representation of internal variables
that like are functional like a
functional representation of
in a functional internal representation
is this like doing um
like you manipulate the variables
internally and then manipulate them
externally like you plan to reach for
the cup to take a drink of water
and then you reach for the cup to take a
drink of water but you have to have like
the internal execution prior to or maybe
simultaneous with the external execution
um is that like
functional representation like you plan
the action and do the action
maybe maybe separate or maybe together
is that what functional representation
looks like
let's go with a reaching for the cup
because as danielle noted like
conversation
improvised spontaneous conversation
of reflexive entities is one of the
hardest
cases
but it's the one that we have so that's
awesome
but we're going to be talking about a
adaptive active inference agent reaching
for a mere active inference agent
so in the sims other paper we discussed
now we're talking about the case of
unidirectional
integration rather than the multi-scale
reciprocal integration so the person is
separated from the cup
there's a separation of the cognitive
model of the agent from the cup
the structural side if the internal
model is
cup-like
or it features a cup variable touching a
table variable and then another edge
that is engaged of the hand touching the
cup for example that might be a
structural similarity
but i think that's part of the debate is
how could there be a structural
similarity when
it's not a cup in your brain which we
kind of talked about last time like how
could you have something that
structurally resembles a car
if
it's your brain and body
the contents related encoding
environmental contingencies or sensory
motor contingencies
so it could be the case that a certain
sensory motor action will result in
picking up and grasping the cup whereas
another sensory motor action
is going to result in the shattering of
the cup and that could be analyzed in
terms of correctness
the functional representational question
would be like
the vicarious detachment
of the sensory motor loop from the
cognition
so then it would be like
if you were to pick up that cup
then
you dumped it what would happen and then
someone says like well water would fall
out
so in that case
it is like there's a functional
representation
whether or not
it resembles the structure of the cup
there's a functional representation
because
that
idea of grasping the cup it's able to be
operated on
internally
vicariously in the absence of direct
stimuli related to the cup
dean
do you mind if i just read right from
the paper for a second because i think
it helps in terms of this the difference
between the sort of the auto automatic
automotive i don't know
automaticity
and reflective aspects of this action
okay
one important implication falling out
falling out of this diagnosis is that
when considering functional rural
aspects
it's often how the details of our chosen
process theories are fleshed out
and contextualized by the kinds of
cognitive phenomena that we are
attempting
to account for
for for that skew
or that for that skew our interpretation
of fep in one direction or another for
example one may consider that there are
core aspects of fep
such as the possession of a markov
blanket and more ancillary aspects and i
think ancillary is the key here such as
the possibility
but not the
necessity to engage in counter factual
inference
which is only required for planning
and it is only the latter more ancillary
aspects that call for
a representational interpretation under
a given process theory this would imply
that when using functional rule as a
sole criterion for representational
processes
only some fbp agents namely those
that can engage in counter factual forms
of inference would meet the criteria for
representation
it is only this subset of fep agents
that would be equated to full-fledged
predictive processing agents so there is
an automaticity part to this
where it's really not a markov blanket
you just do it almost subconsciously and
that's again the authors are trying to
point this out yes if we fail
i drop the cup and now i reflect on that
that's the representational piece
prior to that
i was just going through the motions i
didn't need a set of instructions
telling me to reach out for the cup
so that's just in the author's words
thanks a lot for clarifying that it's
like
yes if one is reflexively
uh grasping at it or accidentally
then
it then grasping the cup like if you're
if you're groping around in a dark room
and then you happen to grasp the cup
it doesn't have to be representational
because
there isn't a counter factual
so
it and that's very interesting how like
they say that it is ancillary
so that's kind of like secondary or um
not
essential to it
because we can imagine an active
inference entity that's taking in
sensory observations updating its
generative model engaging in policy
selection and then resulting in some
action
output impacting the niche and the cycle
begins again
that can be just like a single layer
model that doesn't engage in counter
factuals
but
they raise that notion
that it's only
the counterfactuals
in cognition
that actually like give us the space
to have a functional representation
it's like if the shell just represents
the shell
can't be anything else
but then there's another kind of entity
who can see the shell
as
financial
or can see it in a different way and
then it's those counterfactuals that
enable
the shell to play a functional
representational role
in that it stands for something else
blue what is this
imagery on the bottom
so i just was like trying to really
look at or like try to visualize what
would um these different like
representations really look like right
so if we take like the idea of
two a person and a cup even right okay
so on the first one right we have
organizational so like i am a thirsty
body
i'm contained within me there is the cup
that contains water over there like i
know my boundary i know the boundary of
the cup and the representation looks
like this
um and then a structural representation
um
is just
me
and the
cup and the my relationship between me
and the cup right like so do i have to
also have like like so so my real
question here is
do these perhaps build on one another so
so here you have the structural and um
then the next one would be content
related do i also have to have this
connecting line in the content related
uh is that required like do i have to
have an idea of the structure to
understand the content
and then um in the functional like do
you need to know the content
and the structure and the organizational
to have to have an understanding of the
function right do i need to know like
for the content related like i know that
there's water in the cup right i assume
that there's water in the cup to find
out i have to realize that there's an
inside of me and outside of me and
inside of the cup and outside of the cup
i have to realize my relationship
between me and the cup and then to find
out the content like i have to go
sample the cup like to see what's inside
of it and i have to know what's inside
of me and then the function like like
can i only like i wonder if there's
water in that cup like and then if i go
to drink it and there's like whiskey in
it or something like i'm not gonna
understand the function until i have all
those things layered on top of each
other and so that's kind of really my
question um here in daniel's drawing on
my drawings
but but um
really like i just wonder if there's
levels
of increasing complexity between
these
different kinds of representations or if
it's just merely the structure the
organizational
and i don't need these boundaries
between self and cup
in these other models maybe it's just
the line without the circles in the
structural or or the no external circles
and content related so i just want to
know like what you guys maybe think of
that if there is a layering here because
i was kind of layering them up but i
don't know if that's really the right
mental representation
thanks blue
dean
um
i'm not muted good
i think that i think there's two parts
to this one is that we
are able to differentiate which is what
the table allows for and i think that
the second part is
the the arrow the curved arrow that
daniel drew which essentially
represents
boundary crossing number one
so
the difference between something that's
static and something that is
translatable
and then the second part of it i think
without going back down the rabbit hole
that we almost fell into in in the point
one of this when we started talking
about free will and can and will and the
orthogonal piece of that i think
what it
what it speaks to
maybe
is that it's not a question of free or
or encapsulated it's it's a degree of
dependency question when you when you
throw that curved line on
on this
sort of tiled representation and start
moving across a boundary so i don't want
to call it degrees of dependency will up
to a point of passing through zero but
i'd like to
because i think there is an aspect of
that and that's why i think it's kind of
it's kind of crazy if we just focus on
the static things instead of the moving
around the moving through four squares
is what i really think gives our minds a
good workout
yep so here's another little um workout
so
blue had two circles
in relationship
so here
the circle is going to reflect an
adaptive active inference agent
or the full-fledged predictive
processing agent one that can engage in
counterfactuals so the top is two
adaptive entities in relationship and
the triangle is going to reflect a mere
active inference entity like a cup or
just something that doesn't engage in
counterfactuals
so organizational is the separation of
the systems so that's very similar
because it's just describing there being
a markov blanket separating the systems
the structural representation is having
vehicles that are structurally similar
so it's simple er in the
lower case
triangle out there in the world
is there a structural resemblance that
would be very representational whereas
if they were um cognitively imagining
something different than a triangle that
would have less resemblance
but that gets challenging
with
adaptive adaptive because
we're modeling ourselves modeling each
other blah blah blah
so here's them modeling the conversation
and that's where they're sort of like
very complex dynamics
which is how can we have a structural
similarity about a conversation with
another person but
um it's simpler in the adaptive mirror
case
the content related representations
encode environmental contingencies or
sensory motor contingencies so like in
this case the triangle it is the case
that it can
rotate
clockwise
and so
this entity
does have a good content related
representation
if it can actually turn the dial to that
way
um and again that's a little bit more
complex in the reciprocal
case
but in the unidirectional case
um
this red arrow is a content related
representation of the actual motion in
the world
and then this last case is the
functional representation
and here it still is um
it could be more
structural
so like more about the actual
structure of the cognitive model or it
could be more about the encoding of the
contingencies
but the key piece is this isolation
which isn't a markovian isolation this
is actually the true vicarious
separation of
so here the person or the entity is able
to engage in
either
structural
pondering of the triangle
or
functional pondering of a triangle in
the absence of seeing the triangle or
grasping the triangle
and again though that's a little bit
um
complex when you have multiple
counterfactual cognizers
asking each other questions
i just added a counter factual to you
yeah exactly the red one is um
then there's the blue one it could go a
different way
and then this is this is how we know
that it's a true
cognizer and a true functional
representation yes great call thanks a
lot blue because it has to do with a
vicarious nature
with not directly seeing it
but it also has to do with
that
representation whether more structural
triangular or more functional red arrow
could be different so there's them
having a counter factual
um
[Music]
action contingency and here they're also
imagining
a counterfactual
structural position
okay i'm gonna go to a question from
steven in the chat
steven asked
how do we resolve the use of a term
functional as used in correlational
dynamics
so that's referring to some of our
earlier discussions on like
functional and effective connectivity in
neuroimaging
and the term functional in used
uh and the term functional in terms of
having cognitive counter factuals so how
is
the
functional here
related to
effective and functional connectivity in
neuroimaging
and time series statistics
i'll give a first thought
it's not that it can't be linked or
connected but they are different name
spaces and they're totally different
the functional connectivity in the time
series
is um
about how changes in one variable
through time influence another variable
through time or are associated with
changes in the other one through time so
it's not a mechanistic causal
relationship per se but it's just that
changes in one variable
have an edge reflecting how changes in
some other variable change
that does not engage either of
the pieces that we're highlighting here
which is the vicarious or standing for
nature
nor the counterfactual nature
so it is a different
use of the term functional
functional is an overloaded word
and so yeah it's not that you couldn't
have a paper
that was looking at functional
representation
and using neuroimaging
and using
functional and effective connectivity of
brain regions while
individuals were engaged in functional
representation
but that would a little bit be like the
star was the star of the movie it's just
using a word in multiple senses
in a way that
may
give some
ambiguity to those who don't parse out
the different senses extremely clearly
is that fair to say or does anyone
have a different thought
functional can also mean
teleological
like the function of something
essentially so there's many uses of
function and i think it's um interesting
that it has come up in these different
spaces blue
so i do agree that like they're they're
disconnected but but i
am able to perhaps see a relationship in
like functional connectivity and also in
counter factuals like so when things are
functionally connected
like one drives the other right
um
and then the counter factual is like
when things are not functionally
connected there's no
there's no like you know corresponding
correlation right
so so
in the
exploration of functional connectivity
you have to have all of the data points
like over a time series so you have to
um
like you understand functional
connectivity through the exploration of
counter factuals
does that make sense
okay
how about this functional connectivity
the term
it is a functional representation that
cognitive scientists use
because
it could be otherwise
they're engaging and they're saying
region a and b have functional
connectivity because i did the time
series statistics in spm
and we got this value
and so that functional connectivity
value
is able to be
used in subsequent internal cognitive
representations
it stands for something
and it can be engaged with in a
counter-factual way like what if it
would have been stronger
then what would our conclusion have been
or what if it would have been weaker
what would it have been um
and then stephen wrote um these
definitions these are definitions and
ways to name could be where the ontology
working group could have a future role
yes
ontology development in active inference
and
how
will we even make the decisions of what
terms to use in what senses
disambiguate the uses and the different
corpuses that we are looking at
so
pretty
interesting this graphic actually i hope
any of the authors or anyone who is like
interested in this topic
what do you think about these doodles
do you agree disagree
let's go to blue's question about
autopoiesis what
is like interesting or
not about
just really where it comes in and i
think we kind of brought it up earlier
in our um
in the fairing of a model like like so
is sharing of
a generative model
necessary for self-assembly or even the
attempt to share
a generative model it is that not a
necessary component of auto cohesis
and at what level like organizationally
structurally content related
functionally like at all the levels
um i just wonder like how these things
are related and when we were talking
earlier about having a conversation and
trying to make your models align with
one another through information sharing
and like we saw with um the
computational boundary of itself about
self-assembly and autopoiesis uh via
mike levin um just about the
informational sharing between
subunits leads to the formation of a
larger cognitive unit
and so um
i was just wondering about
model relationships and forming a larger
cognitive unit like we're talking about
the conversation and then we form with
complete overlap of yes we get it we
grok we're there and then we form a
larger cognitive unit
and is that on all aspects is it just
related to content structure
organization or function or all of the
above
just what anybody thinks about that
all right
so
and we saw this actually in matt sims
earlier paper the biological symbiosis
right
yes
the autopoetic system is capable of
producing and maintaining itself by
creating its own parts so it's kind of
like the ship of theseus plus crew
they're able to be modifying and
reconstructing
the material basis of the system
on one hand that maintains an
organizational separation of like the
cell and the surrounding in terms of the
realist interpretation of a markov
blanket
at the same time
the autopoetic process
does not need to have
well
it involves
ingressing and outgressing material
so that does
blur
the boundary
and structurally
it doesn't need to be the case that the
autopoetic process of the cell
has like a blueprint or a structural
resemblance of the cell it could just be
subunits that
are non-representational
they cannot engage
um
[Music]
it doesn't even make sense to ask
whether
the
cognitive model
has structural similarity with the
target
because it's a non-cognitive entity and
similarly
on the functional side
the enzymes can't engage in
counterfactuals
that you know synthesize the lipids and
add them to the membrane
so
is information a representation
i don't know i mean we're getting
getting into the quantum now
so um
yeah where's where's information
in this
it comes up in the paper
um
18 17 times
based on local information
information comprises the generative
model
past and present information future
information information gain no
additional information about internal
states that's the markov definition
high mutual information
can be
um
[Music]
in the context of a non-representational
generalized synchrony like the pendulums
that synchronize
where is the information in this
eightfold distinction
so uh the author talks about here if i
can read a quote quickly
if one only appeals to the
organizational aspect of representation
the presence of environmental or sensory
motor motor or complex or frugal model
does not matter
insofar as the internal variables of the
model are understood to be separated
from external reality by a markov
blanket and the generative model is
leveraged to infer the causal structure
of external reality via self-evidencing
however these differences matter if one
considers structural aspects and the
degree of resemblance between hidden
variables and environmental dynamics as
opposed to action or information
gathering dynamics
so
i don't know here here the content of
representations is used to draw a
further distinction within the
representational view between an
internalist sometimes called
intellectualist or encodist
versus an action-oriented perspective
so
probably one of the most thrilling
academic debates
dean
well
please don't
don't judge what i'm about to say next
just
bear with me be kind so in this
representation for example where we've
got this table
if we were to look at those lines each
one of those horizontal lines because
there's three i see
and each one of those vertical lines
because there's four ic
and we realized and we realized them as
an
a standard x y graph
we know that there's a relationship
between x and y that every one of those
horizontal
lines
relative to y
has a zero component to it
and we know that every one of those
vertical lines relative to x
has a zero component to it
so most people will look at the
blackness of that relative to the white
background and they'll just see
something material separating
but if we actually look at it
graphically and we take daniel's idea of
the tetrahedron every time we round
an edge and change direction on that
tetrahedron there is a zero element
that allows for that boundary crossing
that we again don't pay as much
attention to
and so from a from an autopoetic
standpoint
you can actually see where
something like a mark-up blanket both
separates
and
leaves the potential open
for that transfer or that crossing
or that
transition so
when we're modeling ourselves the last
paragraph
of the section five of the paper they
wrote
arriving at an fep as synthesis
so
some some
[Music]
non-zero number and zero
view depends upon which representational
criterion
we are assuming
when either considering fvp central
constructs or considering specific
cognitive phenomena through the lens of
a process theory under fep
do we include the zero piece of this or
not
tentatively
fully
or do we willfully ignore it
hence in the end the debate about fvp
may reveal more about us
our criteria
whether we want this to be a material
thing and not not include the zero
aspect of it
and our interest in particular facets of
cognition than does about the
representational status of fep
so i just want to kind of bring that
again don't judge me because i i could
be way wrong here and i may be over
fitting
but i think that that auto poetic part
of it
we can see both the separation and we
can see the portal in a line
if we choose to include both
that's kind of what i wanted to bring up
okay
very interesting dean thanks
here's the unfolded tetrahedra there's a
few
unfold there's a few
shapes of paper that can be folded into
a tetrahedra one looks more like a
parallelogram
and one looks more like an equilateral
triangle which just kind of like folds
up like the petals of a flower
so these zero lines
so there's the zero point
of
within a facet
representational and
non-representational that's almost like
the two sides of the paper like how many
triangles are here oh four
how about eight
how many units how many triangle units
of paint do you need to paint this four
no eight two sides so the zero is like
the thickness of the paper and that's
also when you fold it up that's like
inside versus outside of the tet
and then these zero
y lines
are like the movements
from one face to another face
where it's also thin enough as to be
imperceptible
especially when it's laid flat
but it makes all the difference to move
from one side
to another
how do we use
moving through zero
in this
eightfold
or other
cognitive models
how do we use that to increase the
efficacy or the fluidity or the
accessibility
of
models
does it does it help us in explaining
that we're not locked out of that
self-organization
loop
that we can actually participate in it
is that the first thing that it tells us
that we're not
we're not locked out of that ability to
self-generate
that was a question that wasn't that i
wasn't questioning it was it wasn't like
an honest sincere question
i think so
one
supportive or
a complimentary component would be
this is sort of a map this is like a
cognitive map and someone could say this
side of the paper is better than the
other side
and this is my favorite face
but it's presented as part of a larger
knowledge structure
such that the learner could engage in
counter factuals like what if we were on
the other side of the paper or what if
we were on a different face
so
this allows for example
individuals to
reflect
their understanding of the lay of the
land
but also communicate their preferences
and as the paper shows different
individuals
do have different outcomes in terms of
their cognitive conclusions
and that's what reveals the super
fascinating thing about us
and that's why the paper is modeling
ourself
what the free energy reveals about our
implicit notions of representation not
free energy principle modeling
representation what the free energy
principle reveals about representation
which would be a slightly different
paper and title
um
so
just
the
scholarship and the sense making phase
that only very few have to engage in
like sims and pizzulo have
is to make these
maps
and then
bring
the perspectives
that were not
integrated
to be shown as just
different locations in a phase space
like
we put four zeros but
so it's not as simple as just like two
numbers but you know if there was if it
was just two topics being against each
other
every
perspective could have like a position
in that phase space
and then what do we do with that
yes danielle
i guess i'm thinking about the ourselves
part of modeling ourselves i'm not
really thinking about um
all humans and and the way that our
minds work it's more of the the academic
conversations that have been happening
around the sort of intellectual
tradition that's been happening around
representation and so
this the contribution of this paper as i
see it is that look we've got this
framework that does a lot of work for us
in a lot of different disciplines and if
we apply it to this conversation this
intellectual debate
that's been happening we can reveal
implicit assumptions of the debate
itself and
what emerges is that
perhaps does an artifact of particular
examples that have been used to
understand representation um we
see one side of the coin or another we
can see these we pull on these different
dimensions that are laid out in this
paper so
um i guess it's just important to think
about and
disagree if you if you disagree but um
the the ourselves is really just about
the way that philosophers and and
cognitive scientists have been thinking
about this nothing is
true
this is not revealing something about
cognition per se it's it's more about
the implicit assumptions that have been
kind of unfolding and how
how we're thinking about the
discipline
thanks for that
um just like there was a sort of hinge
on the functional being used in two
different ways
another
sense of representation
one that might be more
commonly used outside of cognitive
science would be like representation in
terms of different perspectives or
identities in
a group
and then that made me think of
nothing about us without us
which is used in different contexts but
basically has to do with participatory
decision making that decisions are not
being made
in a way removed from the people who it
influences
and that has to do with representation
no taxation without representation for
example
and so cognitive science is actually in
a
nothing about us without us
because if there's just an academic
discussion especially an unexamined one
with a lot of implicit baggage
about a hyper-intellectualized
hyper-abstracted scenario or like we
like to study representational
organizational cases where it's super
clean these are the ones that we study
these are the model systems these are
the kind of careers that have been built
in academia for example
but it's about
us in the broader sense like humans and
then even us as cognitive entities
and so
it is the philosophers and the
literature
that is in this paper
as danielle kind of highlighted that's
the modeling ourself
the selves there are the participants in
the discussion around
representation which of course has been
textual abstract
english speaking
[Music]
qualitative
other adjectives
so it's another interesting
connection there blue
so definitely like the the subjectivity
that danielle highlighted is
a big part of perhaps why we have these
organizational structural these
different like viewpoints
but um maybe something that i don't
think is really emphasized too much in
this paper
is kind of the the realist versus
instrumentalist viewpoint of active
inference and so
um there's a pretty big argument
um in the literature and i think
probably if the math is not the
territory maybe gets into it the best
maybe or in the most detail
of the papers that we've studied here on
this stream but um
you know there's
people that say like active inference is
a way to model the cognitive process or
the action perception process that we
all undergo and then there are people
who say that this is actually happening
in a computational way
in the brain it's not a model of it is
how it works
and so there's this ongoing um
like
vision fusion feud
happening in the active inference
community also and i just wanted to
highlight that because um
yeah because you may not know
thanks a lot blue i pulled out a few
quotes because i
also noticed that when we it was one of
the earlier quotes when we were talking
about the
um i think
organizational element
so
look at how often reality
comes into play
in these
discussions so internal variables of a
model
okay so we're talking about
instrumentalism right like models
are understood to be separated from
external reality by a markov blanket
wait
reality
and the generative model
model
is leveraged to infer the causal
structure of external
reality
so
it it flips
four times in that sentence
from
reality
from model
to reality
back to model
back to reality
it's a very
it doesn't make it right or wrong
it's just a very interesting epistemic
artifact
because within the reality of the model
like the reality of the map
it is the case that the internal
variables are separated
and if the model is trying to do
determination on that level of reality
like maps trying to infer maps
that is reality
but then
that's not the sort of layer one
external reality in the sense that many
people often mean or use it dean
yeah i think danny if you take the words
reality and model and push them out into
even more
extreme tales
you could you could see the model you
can see people who are pushing back
against the model idea
and they're arguing you're just too
rigid right you're just too stuck and
you can see people that are taking the
non-representational
sort of reality view the the variance
uh maintained or retained view as say
and you can see the people that are on
the model end of the continuum saying
that's just chaos there's nothing about
that that we can actually make sense of
because the cognitive overload right now
is just swamping me
right and so i think what these i think
what these authors were trying to do is
say well
can we move back and forth instead of
getting stuck on those really far out
positions in terms of this
in terms of this um
way of being able to see when we have
these densities
right and then how do those densities
how of those densities re-reset
back to some sort of invariance and then
re-reform
right so i think that's and i hope that
kind of speaks to what daniel was saying
too
because sure we can we can point out the
most extreme example like at the very
end of the continuum
or we can actually talk about how we're
going to draw these
unit direction or bi-directional lines
and boundary cross
and i think that's what they were trying
to open us our thinking up to but
maybe maybe i'm just being pollyanna
here because i really like the paper
adam
interesting point
here's some realism is also used in
another way which is kind of like it's a
school of
literature or a thread of literature
and so then i found this paper affect of
realism
evoke realism beyond representation
and so this is in the case of literary
expression so that's an activity that
cognitive entities are engaged in
and we just see a lot of terms that we
talk about in active
like agency
affect
process
and here it's not about reality
realism territory it's like realization
and realization's an interesting word
and i know verveiki and others use it as
well
because realization
it is about
the model
but when something is realized
it becomes real in the model
but usually we wouldn't say that
something is realized like oh i just
realized that
um
zebras have nine legs
it's like
you engaged in a counter factual
but is it a realization
if the model is updated in a way that
isn't
concordant with reality
and i agree that the paper gives us a
lot of
nuance to talk about these areas because
we can talk about how
well the isolation
of the variables doesn't change or
the structure of the legs and the zebra
doesn't change or
it can still run right
so why not nine legs is it still a zebra
like
there's a lot of open
threads but
the way that they
use
model and reality
in light of a lot of the other
discussions we've had is really
illustrative
blue
so one of my favorite um things to think
about in terms of like the realism
versus the instrumentalism is the markov
blanket and so like i don't was looking
for the picture about like of the person
sleeping under the markov blanket like
like really as a partition for a system
like
do systems have markov blankets or are
they
can they be modeled with markov blankets
like and i always just like think of
that cute little picture with the little
person sleeping under the markup blanket
like do i have a markup blanket wrapped
around me um
because that's really where it um tends
to break down in my mind like yes
there's a boundary
um but i'm not sure that it's
a pristine blanket or a pearl blanket or
a markov blanket like
maybe it's just skin um
yes dean
uh i hate answering a
question with another question but in
the conclusion of the paper
the authors speak specifically to the
free energy principle can be very
heuristic and so i'm wondering
in the instrumentalist versus
versus realist debate whether it has to
necessarily get up to that abstract
level of markov blanket or whether we
can just say that sandwich between those
two are rules
that we de-market that we
we lay down and that we
act have act as a as a parsing mechanism
i don't know what do you think blue
like our rules our rules things that we
can just get our hands on right today
instead of having to go all the way up
to figuring out what a markov blanket is
under this set of circumstances
no i think definitely rules right so i
mean we all agree that there are laws in
physics like if you drop an apple it
will fall to the floor it's like like we
all abide by these rules uh they might
not apply at every scale but um i i
definitely think that a rule-based
construction or understanding like does
that then bridge the realism versus
instrumentalism debate perhaps
[Music]
so
building on the point that the ourselves
in the title is
the people reading
the paper
so not just like people in the psych
department but it's the ourselves the
people who are in that epistemic commons
so
that
but also the
contents related representations
in terms of correctness or truth
so if that if the ourselves
are those who are pondering fep
then
the heuristic
that they refer to we conclude by
highlighting the heuristic power of the
fep to advance our understanding of the
notion of internal representation
it is pretty meta because we're
representing the debate about people
representing the debate about
representation
however
the fact that it has a heuristic utility
within the content related aspect at the
very least
it does have representational
impact i'm not sure where that takes us
there's probably other ways to take it
but i think something about
um
the diversity of conclusions that people
have and how that shines a light back on
us or is a mirror
and how
the fep
has
been applied
here
in this paper
as a heuristic for sense-making
in this meta debate
says something i hope danielle
i i hope i'm addressing what you're
saying and not taking this in another
direction but
i i
stepping back i'm thinking of fep as
just one of many different tools of
thought that we have that allow us to
align our our representations and if it
is an effective tool we all start having
a conversation that makes sense to each
other that's mutually intelligible
um
in this case it is kind of meta because
it's about how
the academics the intellectual
conversation about representations
um have
failed to converge on something there's
this debate there are many layers of the
debate and so what it reveals is that we
haven't yet converged that the community
hasn't converged and so fep is
is this thing that we can use that
reveals those things and allows us to
then better because it's revealing these
things we can all attend to those things
that were implicit and are now made
explicit we're converging
our representations so i think that kind
of addresses what you're saying it's
about representations but it's also this
this tool like there are many other
types of tools
that allow us to
realize what we've been taking for
granted and align our our
representations
thanks a lot dean
yeah and just just add on to that
if you're like me you think
rules and tools are
are interchangeable
and the other thing you think is that
if it's a heuristic it speaks kind of
that to that vicarious function
in terms of content
so i i just want to throw that on top
because i think there's some agreement
around that
we use the rules to make that next very
like vicarious
play
the next before we make the next move
so
i mean anybody that doesn't are just
kind of kidding themselves i think but
maybe i'm wrong
okay here's a little bit of fep in a
heuristic
case so we've talked about the helmholtz
decomposition
of vector fields like in
stream number 32
about how there's this pragmatic
or sort of hill climbing or gradient
descending component whether you take
the optimistic biology climbing mountain
probable go straight up the mountain of
fitness or the physicist's
gradient descent into the bottom of the
well
in either case there's that irrotational
component that's associated with
pragmatism
and then there's this epistemic
component that's associated with the
solenoidal isocontour so we've talked
about that helmholtz decomposition
so here's one way in which the fep is
being heuristically applied
so danielle said
the academic conversation on
representation has not converged and it
it has not converged and it has also not
even
cohered
like there isn't a shared ontology
there's not a shared narrative there's
not shared words or regime of attention
or what people are even focused on
and so
what the fep is doing
literally like they did here
with this
distinction
it does a few things it it holds space
for not overfitting like let's just say
in 2055 all the people in the world or
all the cognitive scientists they all
agreed oh great we converged
let's lock that in
but
fep even then
will remind us like not to over fit
and also not to center one side of the
tetrahedra we could say this is the side
that has these attributes or we focus on
this side for these reasons
um and no one goes there to this other
side or there's a reason why we don't go
there or we take a journey we travel
through there but we don't live there or
something like that
it
brings a level of coherence to the
discussion
that
doesn't necessarily have the goal of
perfect static convergence
but
still there'll be
solenoidal flow
and differences in opinion even then
um
[Music]
who said the fbp wasn't useful
well and maybe this is obvious but is is
that not what any good theory does like
blue said well gravity is true because
if i drop an apple it will fall yeah so
the theory of gravity does the same
thing it allows us to
kind of converge our representations
it's just that the theory of gravity is
not itself about representation
yes
this
this is like the hall of mirrors this
paper and conversation because it is
like
it's the group of people in the
holobeers and they're all wearing mirror
suits
in a weird way but
it is our
gym
for building
the kind of
frameworks that then can reduce our
uncertainty a ton
potentially in similar cases
and the strange loop of reflexive
cognitive entities
is gonna be this
open-ended fount
for a long time to come
but just like how we started here
with a really
complex reciprocal case of two adaptive
entities
but then it was a lot less ambiguous
here
and i wonder if um
active informed system design
will frame an increasing
amount of pieces especially in a digital
world
into this bottom
tier
offloading
some of the
repetitive tasks attention consuming
tasks
anxiety producing
stimuli
into these type of interactions
which opens up new spaces for these
kinds of interactions
with the two adaptive entities
to return to that having her possessing
a markov blanket just one quick point
was which we already even read the quote
which was a core aspect of fep such as
the possession of a markov blanket
so
is
the markov blanket the system
or does it have one those are both
realist or is it modeled as having is it
modeled as being those are
instrumentalist ways of similar framings
and how do we know what the core aspects
are
what
does that stem from
so there's a ton to learn and discuss
there
and then let's look at any in just our
last few minutes any of the other topics
and
if anybody wants to highlight one of
these or also maybe
as we jump off from
36.2
to 37 and beyond
when we discuss
free energy a user's guide but also we
just continue on our paths like
why does it matter
not all these
papers
maybe make the argument for why this
whole representation debate matters
so what is the pragmatics
that make this meaningful make it
important to
fund people working on it or the way
that influences the technologies that
we're developing
rather than just a pure
info gain reduction of uncertainty
question
so any topics here
or any like thoughts on how this
will or could or should
influence our action selection going
forward
i'm comfortable with long silences but
i'm gonna
i'm gonna throw this out there i think
i think people will be able to use this
tool to become more creative not just be
able to reduce their minute minimum
reduce or minimize
their prediction errors
but actually have the confidence is to
come up with new
and different ways of looking at
problems that we probably didn't have in
our
in our toolkit
before in terms of being able to come up
with
something different
and so i think
um
the first thing that it does is it
allows for a boundary crossing that
that
maybe we constructed in our minds before
but
we're seeing less and less of it as
being a a hard
stop
and there's now
maybe a little bit more
more say in whether to go or no or don't
go so that's what i would think that
this kind of work is is is maybe
opening up unless somebody comes and
shuts it down
and i can't speak to what outside forces
would find terribly threatening but i'm
sure there are some out there
outside
blue
so i'm not sure if this has any
pragmatic value but i'm i'm certainly
interested in um kind of really
exploring like
sensory motor engagement and structural
representation and maybe like
synesthesia um i know daniel's been to
meow wolf but like you know when you're
playing these invisible like the
invisible harp you know and like could
you structure a room like draw a map in
a room and your goal is to like kind of
like an escape room but your goal is to
find navigate your way through
uh based on sound right like you ting
the things and you have to find the
right sound you play mary had a little
lamb and then you get to your prize at
the end or you get to get out of the
room and so as i wonder creatively like
that like um dean was saying like really
these maps um these representations can
we get literally out of our own
representation and into
the feeling of an alternate
representation and what would that feel
like or be like and that's also why i
brought up like blindness like you know
if you ever wake up in like a totally
like my power went out the other night
it was like black i mean no moon nothing
like it was just like whoa total
darkness right like no little blue light
from the plug or nothing right so
um in these like total darkness
situations you have this representation
of like what does my house look like
where's my flashlight like you have to
be able to navigate yourself in a
totally dark situation it's which is
very foreign to go find a flashlight and
so i i like these kind of boundary
pushing um
experiences and because they really
force us to
examine our own model and perhaps allow
us to explore the kind of models that
other people use
thinking through other minds
is
this case with adaptive agents in
dialogue
and it's it's like thinking through
other
representations and
this paper and discussion
opens up
not to then
simply converge but opens up and holds
ways
to think and act through other
types of representations not just the
same type but in a different cognitive
entity
it comes up
a lot
and it'd be awesome to see how
just as so many other themes that we've
had raised by very prescient papers
like
14. math is not the territory 20
emperor's new markov blanket and some of
the further nuancing
about
the markovian assumptions
this
representational and
non-representational and these words
like organization structure content and
function
they will come up again and maybe
they'll be citing
this paper
maybe they won't
but like
it's almost like when we see in a future
paper just one facet
of the tet and they'll say here's how it
is it's this one side it's like well no
there's other sides and we could be
inside or we could be outside
and someone could still say i prefer
this one but
we know there's a bigger
system that we can at least
come to the
table around dean
i'm not
marketing but it's going to come up in
37.
it's going to come up a bunch of times
in 37 so that's just the next paper
so anyway hold on your socks because if
you think you have to wait for it to
come up again it's going to come back up
again next week
so
don't touch that dial
thanks a lot for the awesome
sequence this was a
somewhat
complex or
intellectual paper
i mean they're all written but this one
was like
challenging topics a lot of different
perspectives
and then not only did they
hold
it open
for all of the different perspectives
but then
rather than pick a winner
they flipped
the table in the end
and
posed it not as an answered
competition
for us to then
have
um like domain specific clarity of
action within
but really a challenge
on multiple levels
for
researchers
who are familiar with fep
and not
the big question we asked was can the
free energy principle help us advance or
even resolve the long lasting debate on
internal representation in philosophy of
mind
we certainly asked
so
if anybody has any last comments they
want to make
on
anything
they're welcome to
give somebody else the last word so i'll
get this in real quick i think that if
we're still arguing about whether or not
representation and modeling is heavily
dependent
like that there is a dependency
i think that the more
philosophical
views that we
see
come up around fep and active inference
the harder and harder it is
to make the case that we can
remove that dependency or somehow just
see the scale-free aspects of this tool
that there's actually a
heavy dependency on what we're going to
get out of representation or
non-representation
based on our awareness or our
realization that every time we cross a
boundary
that is just an independent act that's a
highly dependent act so that'll be my
last word
so i just want to give a final comment
you know we talk about instrumentalism
and realism and then there's like the
third axis right of utility
and i really think that this paper was
super useful in prompting new questions
and holding up these different views of
representation and non-representation
and in these different categories and
and allowing us to really kind of
view them through like a partitioned
framework uh um that i think will drive
future questions and um and really be
useful in helping researchers formulate
their theories
great
danielle if you're still here
thanks for joining for your first
stream do you have any last comments
oh this was a wonderful introduction
i'm curious how representative it is of
of other conversations it was super
heady in in a really uh pleasant way
it was not representative or
representational of other conversations
no
thanks a lot for the awesome convo
everyone's always welcome to join these
discussions or other lab activities so
thanks again to the authors and all the
participants here
c